Private Press Specimens Collection
Private Press Specimens Collection
circa 1962-1975
0.25 linear ft.
various small items printed by private presses in the United States, including broadsides, booklets, catalogs, prospectuses, and ephemera
5471338
Biographical History
Private presses are small independent printers, often run by one or two individuals, whose focus is on typography, design, and craftsmanship rather than sales and profit. Items are produced by hand using traditional printing equipment and high-quality (sometimes handmade) paper and ink. Their output is valued by collectors for its artistry and quality.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Private Press Specimens Collection contains examples of printing from private presses across the United States, including Black Sparrow Press, Crabgrass Press, Encino Press, and Tenfingers Press. Types of material include broadsides, booklets, catalogs, prospectuses, and ephemera.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical.
Related Material
has numerous collections relating to printing and book arts. Please refer to or to locate related material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Publishing, printing and book arts; Adagio Press.; Black Sparrow Press.; Broadside Press.; Crabgrass Press.; Cranium Press.; Encino Press.; Grabhorn-Hoyem (Firm); Four Ducks Press.; David R. Godine, Publisher.; Perishable Press Limited.; Red Hill Press.; Stone Wall Press.; Tenfingers Press.; Twowindows Press.; Windhover Press (Iowa City, Iowa); Private presses -- United States.; Booklets.; Broadsides (notices); Catalogs (documents); Leaflets.; Pamphlets.; Prospectuses.; Printers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 2013.
Inventory
- Presses, by name
  - Adagio Press, Harper Woods MI, 1970-1971; undated (Box 1)
  - Black Sparrow Press, Los Angeles CA, undated (Box 1)
  - Broadside Press, Detroit, MI, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Crabgrass Press, Praire Village KS, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - Cranium Press,San Francisco CA, undated (Box 1)
  - Encino Press, Austin TX, 1967; undated (Box 1)
  - Four Ducks Press, Wichita KS, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Godine Press, Brookline MA, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Grabhorn-Hoyem, San Francisco CA, 1965; undated; includes one item printed by Hoyem independently (Box 1)
  - Perishable Press, Ltd, Madison and Mount Horeb WI, 1967-1969; undated (Box 1)
  - Red Hill Press, Fairfax CA, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Stone Wall Press, Iowa City IA, undated (Box 1)
  - Tenfingers Press, Los Angeles CA, 1964-1968; undated (Box 1)
  - Two Windows Press, san Francisco CA, undated (Box 1)
  - Windhover Press, [1969?] (Box 1)
- Presses, unidentified
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)